Sean J. O'Sullivan

Sean.OSullivan@austin.utexas.edu

EDUCATION	
University of Texas at Austin	6/2022-present
Austin, TX	
Psychiatry Residency (currently PGY-1)	
Sidney Kimmel Medical College of Thomas Jefferson University	7/2013-5/2021
Philadelphia, PA	,,
MD/PhD	
PhD Neuroscience GPA 4.0	Defended: Spring 2019
Pennsylvania State University	2012
Brandywine, PA	
Premedical Sciences Program, GPA 3.98	
University of Pittsburgh	8/2006-5/2010
Pittsburgh, PA	0/2000 5/2010
Bachelor of Science in Neuroscience with Departmental Honors	
Minor in Chemistry and French	
GPA 3.74, Magna Cum Laude	
AWARDS AND HONORS	
University of Texas at Austin	
American Psychiatric Association Research Colloquium Fellowship	2023
Psychiatry Resident-In-Training Examination (PRITE) Fellowship nomi	nee 2023
Sidney Kimmel Medical College	
Distinction in Scholarly Inquiry	2020
Longitudinal Integrated Clerkship at Atlantic Health Systems	2019-2020
Jefferson College of Life Science Alumni Association Graduate Student	
National Institute on Alcohol Abuse and Alcoholism Ruth L. Kirschstein	
Service Award Institutional Research Training Grant (T32)	2016-2017, 2018-2019
AOA Research Symposium – Runner-up best poster	2016
AOA Research Symposium – Podium Presentation	2015 2014-2021
Hobart Amory Hare Honor Society Mignon W. Dubbs and Alfred W. Dubbs Fellowship	2014-2021
wighon w. Dubbs and Africa w. Dubbs renowship	2013-2021
Penn State University	
Dean's List	2011-2012
Certificate of Recognition for Outstanding Academic Achievement	2012
University of Pittsburgh	
Neuroscience Departmental Honors	2010
Chancellor's Undergraduate Research Fellowship	2009
Dean's List	2006-2010
Dean's Star	2008
RESEARCH EXPERIENCE	

University of Texas at Austin, Austin, TX

7/2022-present

Principle Investigator: Charles Nemeroff, MD, PhD; Chair of Department of Psychiatry and Human Behavior

- IV Ketamine for Treatment of Major Depressive Disorder Meta-Analysis (In Progress) Principle Investigator: Peter Zandi, PhD; Department of Psychiatry and Behavioral Sciences at Johns Hopkins University in collaboration with Jorge Almeida, MD, PhD; Department of Psychiatry and Human Behavior at UT Austin
 - Open-label clinical trial of Stanford Neuromodulation Therapy (SNT) in bipolar depression
 - o Safety concerning potential manic conversion
 - o Neuroimaging biomarkers and differences between bipolar depression and MDD

Stanford University School of Medicine, Palo Alto, CA

5/2021-6/2022

Brain Stimulation Lab

Principle Investigator: Dr. Nolan Williams, MD; Department of Psychiatry and Human Behavior **Projects**

- Inpatient Clinical Trials
 - Leader of Phase II Trial treating acute manic episodes with SNT
 - o Supporting Phase II Trial treating borderline personality disorder with SNT
 - o Supporting Phase III Trial treating acute suicidality with SNT
- Outpatient studies
 - Leader of study investigating acetyl-L-carnitine as a biomarker of treatment resistant depression and predictor of response to SNT
 - Supporting Phase I Trial treating traumatic brain injury in military veterans with psychedelic intervention ibogaine

Highlights

- Substantial time spent on Stanford Inpatient Psychiatric Service interacting with attending physicians, residents, and patients.
- Reviewing medical records to assess study eligibility of psychiatric inpatients
- Applying accelerated intermittent theta burst stimulation to study participants
- Measuring participant response to SNT with TMS-EEG
- Working with T1 MRI and resting-state fMRI images to determine brain functional connectivity and functional targets for SNT treatment
- Administering assessments to clinical trial participants including Structured Clinical Interview for DSM Disorders, Mini International Neuropsychiatric Interview, and depression, mania and borderline scales including MADRS and HAM-D 17
- Writing clinical protocols and amendments for IRB approval

Thomas Jefferson University, Philadelphia PA

8/2015-4/2021

Daniel Baugh Institute for Functional Genomics and Computational Biology
Principle Investigator: Dr. James S. Schwaber PhD; Director of Daniel Baugh Institute **Dissertation** – The Effect of Alcohol and Opioid Withdrawal on Single-Cell Glia and Neuronal
Gene Expression in the Visceral Emotional Neuraxis

Defended: April 4, 2019

www.jefferson.edu/about/news-and-events/2019/8/the--inflammation--of-opioid-use.html

Projects

- Gene expression in single neurons, microglia, and astrocytes in the central nucleus of the amygdala in opioid withdrawal
- Gene expression in single neurons and microglia in the nucleus tractus solitarius in alcohol withdrawal

- Role of gut microbiome dysbiosis in drug addiction via negative reinforcement
- Gene expression in single neurons in the suprachiasmatic nucleus following phase shift
- Diurnal gene expression differences in the amygdala and nucleus tractus solitarius in both control and alcohol-dependent rats
- MicroRNA influence on gene networks in rat model of hypertension

Highlights

- Rodent work feeding, surgery, experimental models, and tissue harvesting
- Molecular biology laser capture microdissection, RT-qPCR, Western blot, immunohistochemistry, confocal imaging
- Computational biology statistical and multivariate analyses of high dimensional datasets with R, Cytoscape, Matlab, and Multiple Experiment Viewer

Major Scientific Conferences Attended

Society for Neuroscience (SfN)	2017, 2019
Experimental Biology (EB)	2019
American Academy of Neurology (AAN) Annual Meeting	2019
National Institute of Drug Abuse (NIDA) Genetics Consortium	2018

Fox Chase Cancer Center, Philadelphia PA

2012-2013

Department of Psychosocial and Biobehavioral Medicine

Principle Investigator: Dr. Suzanne M. Miller, PhD; Director, Patient Empowerment and Decision Making; Editor and Chief, Translational Behavioral Medicine, Society of Behavioral Medicine

Research Assistant

- Developed a data-driven website designed to guide and educate prostate cancer survivors on side effects following treatments
- Responsibilities: identify eligible subjects using electronic medical record, interview
 prostate cancer patients post-treatment, transcribe interviews, support user testing of
 website, modify website based on feedback, communicate with team members from
 multiple sites on findings and website development, meeting minutes

Principle Investigator: Dr. Sui-Kuen Azor Hui, PhD, MSPH

Research Assistant

• Early-stage development of project aimed at increasing enrollment of ethnic minorities in cancer prevention clinical trials through Employee Wellness Programs

University of Pittsburgh, Pittsburgh PA

2008-2010

Department of Neuroscience

Principle Investigator: Jon W. Johnson, PhD; Professor of Neuroscience and Psychiatry **Undergraduate student researcher**

Thesis - Inhibition of the of N-methyl D-Aspartate Receptor by Memantine is Dependent on Agonist Duration

Defended: April, 2010

- Electrophysiology, cell culture, and transfection
- Whole-cell voltage-clamp experiments on genetically modified human embryonic kidney (HEK) cells
- Investigated mechanism of inhibition of memantine on *N*-methyl-D-aspartate (NMDA) receptors
- Responsibilities: performing transfections, electrophysiology recording experiments, data collection and organization, maintaining and troubleshooting equipment, calibrating equipment, analyzing and presenting findings in lab meetings and research conferences

PUBLICATIONS

- **O'Sullivan, S.J.**, Cole, E., Tik, M, Williams, NR. (2023) The Acceleration of Theta Burst Stimulation (TBS) Protocols. Biol Psychiat. In Revision.
- **O'Sullivan, S.J.**, Buchanan, D., Batail, JM V. (2023) Considering rTMS as a First-Line Treatment for Major Depressive Episodes in Adults. In submission.
- O'Sullivan, S.J. & Lazar E.L. (2022) Medicalese and its Discontents. In submission.
- **O'Sullivan, S.J.**, Srivastava, A., Vadigepalli R, Schwaber JS. (2022) Investigating Drivers of Antireward in Addiction Behavior with Anatomically Specific Single-Cell Gene Expression Methods. J Vis Exp. 186
- **O'Sullivan, S.J.** (2021) Understanding the regulation of transcription in mental illness. OMB Genetics. 5(4): 7
- **O'Sullivan, S.J.,** McIntosh-Clarke D, Park J, Vadigepalli R, Schwaber JS. (2021) Single Cell Scale Neuronal and Glial Gene Expression and Putative Cell Phenotypes and Networks in the Nucleus Tractus Solitarius in an Alcohol Withdrawal Time Series. Front Syst Neurosci. 15: 739
- **O'Sullivan, SJ**. (2021) Single-cell systems neuroscience: A growing frontier in mental illness. Biocell. 10.32604
- **O'Sullivan, SJ**. (2021) The interoceptive antireward pathway and gut dysbiosis in addiction. J Psychiatry Depress Anxiety. 10.24966/PDA-0150/100040
- **O'Sullivan, S.J.** & Schwaber JS. (2021) Similarities in alcohol and opioid withdrawal syndromes suggest common negative reinforcement mechanisms involving the interoceptive antireward pathway. Neurosci Biobehav Rev. 125(6): 355.
- **O'Sullivan, S.J.**, Reyes, B.A.S., Vadigepalli, R., Van Bockstaele, E.J., Schwaber, J.S. (2020) Combining Laser Capture Microdissection and Microfluidic qPCR to Analyze Transcriptional Profiles of Single Cells: A Systems Biology Approach to Opioid Dependence. J Vis Exp. 10: 3791/60612.
- Staehle, M.M., **O'Sullivan**, **S.J.**, Vadigepalli, R., Kernan, K., Gonye, G.E., Ogunnaike, B.A., Schwaber, J.S. (2020) Diurnal patterns of gene expression in the dorsal vagal complex and the central nucleus of the amygdala non-rhythm-generating brain regions. Front Neurosci. 10: 375.
- **O'Sullivan, S.J.**, Malahias, E., Park, J., Srivastava, A., Reyes, B.A.S., Gorky, J., Vadigepalli, R., Van Bockstaele, E.J., Schwaber, J.S. (2019) Single-cell glia and neuron gene expression in the central amygdala in opioid withdrawal suggests inflammation with correlated gut dysbiosis. Front Neurosci. 13: 665.
- Park, J., Zhu, H., **O'Sullivan, S.J.**, Ogunnaike, B.A., Weaver, D.R., Schwaber, J.S., Vadigepalli R. (2016) Single-Cell Transcriptional Analysis Reveals Novel Neuronal Phenotypes and Interaction Networks Involved in the Central Circadian Clock. Front Neurosci. 10: 481.

POSTER PRESENTATIONS

- **O'Sullivan, S.J.**, Li, K., Reti, I., Almeida, J., Zandi, P. "Neuroimaging Biomarkers in Bipolar Depression and Stanford Neuromodulation Therapy: An Open-Label Feasibility Study," American Psychiatric Association, Annual Meeting, 2023.
- Cho, D., O'Sullivan, S.J., Casillas, M.M., Ortiz, N. "Establishing an Evidenced Based rTMS-iTBS Treatment Protocol for Major Depressive Disorder over the Left Dorsolateral Prefrontal Cortex," University of Texas at Austin, Scholarly Day, Spring 2023
- **O'Sullivan, S.J.**, Park, J., Malahias, E., Reyes, B.A., Van Bockstaele, E.J., Schwaber, J.S. "Opioid Withdrawal Shifts Amygdalar Transcriptome and is Correlated with Gut Dysbiosis," Society for Neuroscience, Fall 2019.
- **O'Sullivan, S.J.**, Park, J., Malahias, E., Reyes, B.A., Van Bockstaele, E.J., Schwaber, J.S. "Opioid Withdrawal Shifts Amygdalar Transcriptome and is Correlated with Gut Dysbiosis," American Academy of Neurology, Spring 2019.
- **O'Sullivan, S.J.**, Schuck, R., Tonnesen, S., Sallade, G., Osisek, E., Ubhi, A., "Bridging the Gaps: Team 6 Hotspotting Experience," Student Hotspotting Wrap-Up Capstone, Spring 2019
- **O'Sullivan, S.J.**, McIntosh-Clark, D., Park, J., Vadigepalli, R., Schwaber, J.S. "Single Neuron and Microglia Gene Expression Networks Demonstrate Cellular Subphenotype Shifts and Altered Glial-Neuronal Signaling in Solitary Nucleus During Alcohol Withdrawal: A Time Series," Experimental Biology 2019, Spring 2019.
- **O'Sullivan, S.J.**, Malahias, E., Gorky, J., Park, J., Schwaber, J.S., Reyes, B.A., Van Bockstaele, E.J., Schwaber, J.S. "Transcriptional Analysis of Single Neurons and Glia in the Amygdala in Morphine-dependence and following 24 hours of Morphine Withdrawal," Thomas Jefferson University, Sigma Xi Student Research Day, Spring 2018.
- **O'Sullivan, S.J.**, Reyes, B.A., Van Bockstaele, E.J., Schwaber, J.S. "Sex Differences in Gene Expression in the Amygdala in Morphine Dependence and Withdrawal," Society for Neuroscience, Fall 2017.
- **O'Sullivan, S.J.**, Park, J., Malahias, E., Reyes, B.A., Van Bockstaele, E.J., Schwaber, J.S. "Opioid Withdrawal Shifts Amygdalar Transcriptome and is Correlated with Gut Dysbiosis," National Institutes of Health, National Institute of Drug Abuse (NIDA) Genetics Consortium, Spring 2017.
- **O'Sullivan, S.J.**, Park, J., Malahias, E., Reyes, B.A., Van Bockstaele, E.J., Schwaber, J.S. "Single-cell analysis of Amygdala in Opiate Exposure and Withdrawal Correlates to Gut Dysbiosis," Thomas Jefferson University, Sigma Xi Student Research Day, Spring 2016.
- **O'Sullivan, S.J.**, Malahias, E., Gorky, J., Park, J., Schwaber, J.S. "Neuroinflammation and Gut Dysbiosis following Morphine Exposure and Withdrawal: Implications in Addition," Thomas Jefferson University, AOA Research Symposium, Spring 2016. Runner up.
- **O'Sullivan, S.J.**, Park, J., Zhu, H., Schwaber, J.S., Vadigepalli, R. "Gene Expression Profiles of Suprachiasmatic Nucleus Neurons Provide Insight into the Master Clock," Thomas Jefferson University, Sigma Xi Student Research Day, Spring 2015.

O'Sullivan, S.J., Johnson, J.W. "Dependence on Agonist Application Duration of *N*-methyl D-Aspartate Receptor Inhibition by Memantine," University of Pittsburgh, Honors College Undergraduate Research Fair, Spring 2010.

PODIUM PRESENTATIONS

O'Sullivan, S.J., Li, K., Reti, I., Almeida, J., Zandi, P. "Neuroimaging Biomarkers in Bipolar Depression and Stanford Neuromodulation Therapy: An Open-Label Feasibility Study," American Psychiatric Association, Annual Meeting, 2023.

O'Sullivan, S.J., Park, J., Zhu, H., Schwaber, J.S., Vadigepalli, R. "Reexamining Neuronal Subtypes in the Master Clock; I Dream of Gene Networks," Thomas Jefferson University, AOA Research Symposium, Spring 2015.

WORK EXPERIENCE

TOTAL BILL BRIDITE	
Stanford University, Post-doctoral clinical research fellow	2021-2022
Thomas Jefferson University, Instructor in Medical Genetics	2017
The Princeton Review, MCAT Instructor in Biology and Chemistry	2012-2019
ESL Teacher – Giraffe American English School, Taiwan	2010-2011